Finding Aid for Owen J. Cleary Papers 1944-1959
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Owen J. Cleary Papers 1944-1959
Cleary, Owen J., 1900-1960.
Owen J. Cleary was an attorney, president of Cleary College in Ypsilanti (1940-1960), Michigan secretary of state (1953-1954), and chairman of the Republican State Central Committee (1949-1953). The collection includes correspondence, scrapbooks and clippings, organizational files, and Republican Party files.
851040 Aa 2; AC; Ac
10 linear feet
2 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Owen J. Cleary (donor no. 3947 ) in 1962.
The collection is open for research.
Cleary was born February 4, 1900 in Ypsilanti, Michigan. His father was the founder of Cleary College, a business college located in Ypsilanti, Michigan. Following service in World War I, Cleary graduated from law school and established the firm of Cleary & Weins with offices both in Ypsilanti and Detroit. During World War II, he commanded the Michigan State Troops as brigadier general and after the war, he had charge of the reorganization of the Michigan National Guard.
Cleary was a life-long Republican who served in various capacities within government and within the party. From 1947 to 1949, he was chairman of the Michigan Liquor Control Commission where he helped reorganize the purchasing and enforcement division of that commission. Cleary was also a member of the Washtenaw County Tax Allocation Board, secretary of the Washtenaw County Republican Committee, Ypsilanti Republican chairman and Washtenaw County chairman. Much of his later career was devoted to his work as president of Cleary College.
Cleary died September 10, 1960.
The collection documents the later period of Cleary's life, mainly from 1945 to 1959. The series include Correspondence; Scrapbooks and clippings; Organizational interests; and Political files.
The great bulk of the collection consists of correspondence dated from 1945 to 1959 and documenting his work as Republican State chairman (1949-1953), his tenure as Michigan secretary of state (1953-1954), and his various other civic, political, and business involvements. There is included with this finding aid a selective index to Cleary's correspondents.
Subjects:
American Legion. Dept. of Michigan.; Cleary College (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Cleary, Owen J., 1900-1960.; Elections--Michigan--1950.; Elections--Michigan--1952.; Elections--Michigan--1954.; Elections--Michigan--1956.; Lawyers--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Michigan. Liquor Control Commission.; Michigan. Dept. of State.; Michigan. National Guard.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Politicians--Michigan.; Presidents--United States--Election--1952.; Presidents--United States--Election--1956.; Republican Party (Mich.); Republican Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.; Ypsilanti (Mich.); United States--Politics and government--1953-1961.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1953.; Universities and colleges--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Cleary, Owen J., 1900-1960.; Political elections--1952.; Soldiers--American.; World War, 1939-1945.
Contributors:
Alger, Frederick Moulton, 1907-1967.; Aten, Murl K., 1901-1971; Bagwell, Paul D.; Bennett, John B. (John Bonifas), 1905-1964.; Bentley, Alvin M. (Alvin Morell), 1918-1969.; Blackney, William Wallace, 1876-1963.; Bliss, Ray Charles, 1907-1981.; Brake, D. Hale, 1891-1979; Brownell, Herbert, 1904-1996; Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Capehart, Homer E. (Homer Earl), 1897-1979.; Carr, Leland W. (Leland Walker), 1883-1969; Case, Francis H. (Francis Higbee), 1896-1962.; Cederberg, Elford Alfred, 1918-; Chamberlain, Charles E. (Charles Ernest), 1917-2002; Cobo, Albert E. (Albert Eugene), 1893-1957.; Dirksen, Everett McKinley.; Dondero, George Anthony, 1883-1968.; Duff, James H. (James Henderson), 1883-1969.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Engel, Albert Joseph, 1888-1959.; Farrell, Lawrence Llewellyn, 1903-1971.; Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Ford, Henry, 1917-1987.; Gabrielson, Guy George, 1891-; Hall, Leonard W. (Leonard Wood), 1900-1979; Halleck, Charles A. (Charles Abraham), 1900-1986.; Hannah, John A., 1902-1991; Hare, James M. (James McNeil), 1910-1980; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.; Hatcher, Harlan, 1898-1998.; Hershey, Lewis Blaine, 1893-1977; Hoffman, Clare Eugene, 1875-1967.; Hunt, H. L.; Jenner, William E. (William Ezra), 1908-1985; Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971.; Knox, Victor Alfred, 1899-; Kohler, Walter J., Jr. (Walter Jodok), 1904-1976; Lodge, Henry Cabot, Jr., 1902-1985; McCarthy, Joseph, 1908-1957.; McDonald, Harry A., 1894-1964.; McNamara, Patrick Vincent, 1894-1966.; Martin, John Butlin, 1909-; Martin, Joseph William, 1884-1968.; Meader, George, 1907-1994; Mechem, E. L. (Edwin Leard), 1912-2002; Michener, Earl C. (Earl Cory), 1876-1957.; Millard, Frank G. (Frank Gurnee), 1897-1976.; Milliken, William G., 1922-; Miriani, Louis C.; Mitchell, James Paul, 1900-1964.; Mundt, Karl E. (Karl Earl), 1900-1974; Munn, Clarence Lester, 1908-; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Pollock, James K. (James Kerr), 1898-1968; Potter, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1916-1979.; Pyle, Howard, 1906-1987; Rogers, William P. (William Pierce), 1913-2001; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Roth, Stephen John, 1908-; Russell, Richard B. (Richard Brevard), 1897-1971.; Scott, Hugh, 1900-1994; Shafer, Paul W. (Paul Werntz), 1893-1954.; Sigler, Kim, b. 1894.; Sink, Charles A. (Charles Albert), 1879-1972.; Sligh, Charles R., Jr. (Charles Robert), 1906-1997; Stassen, Harold E. (Harold Edward), 1907-2001; Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-1972.; Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953.; Thompson, Ruth, 1887-1970.; Vandenberg, William C.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Wolcott, Jesse Paine, 1893-1969.; Woodruff, Roy Orchard, 1876-1953.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1945-May 1950 (Box 1)
  - June 1950-August 1951 (Box 2)
  - September 1951-July 1952 (Box 3)
  - August 1952-December 1952 (Box 4)
  - January 1953-August 1954 (Box 5)
  - September 1954-September 1956 (Box 6)
  - October 1956-1959 (Box 7)
- Scrapbooks and clippings
  - Newspaper clippings, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, 5 folders (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook: campaign for state secretary of state 1952 (Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook 1944-1954 (Volume 2)
- Organizational interests
  - Cleary College (Box 8)
  - United Consumers League (Box 8)
  - Law firm (financial material) (Box 8)
  - American Legion-National Defense Commission (Box 8)
  - Council for National Security (Box 8)
  - Michigan Liquor Control Commission, 5 folders (Box 8)
  - Wine Institute (Box 8)
  - Michigan National Guard (Box 8)
  - Michigan Secretary of State press releases 1953-1954 (Box 8)
  - Willow Run Airport 1955 (Box 9)
  - Printed material and miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 9)
- Political files
  - William C. Vandenberg Gubernatorial Campaign 1952 (Box 9)
  - Campaign Schedules 1952 (Box 9)
  - Republican National Committee materials (Box 9)
  - Republican State Central Committee materials, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Canvasses of Michigan Votes (Box 9)
  - Lincoln Day (Box 9)
  - Committee on Interstate Cooperation (Box 9)
  - Republican National Finance Committee (Box 9)
  - Republican State Convention
    - February 1951 (Box 9)
    - April 1, 1952 (Box 9)
  - American Veterans Committee (Box 9)
  - Fighters for Freedom (Box 9)
  - Kelly Recount 1950 (Box 9)
  - Press Releases 1951-1952 (Box 9)
  - Speeches (Box 9)
  - Republican State Convention April 5, 1952 (Box 9)
  - Republican State Convention August 16, 1952 (Box 9)
  - 1952 campaign materials (Box 9)
  - Republican National Convention 1952 (Box 9)
  - Fred M. Alger Recount 1952 (Box 9)
  - 1956 campaign (Box 9)
  - Cleary Gubernatorial Campaign 1954 (Box 9)
  - General Campaign Material 1956 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous political materials, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous political materials, 6 folders (Box 10)
  - Political advertising (Box 10)
- Miscellaneous
  - Photographs (Box 10)
  - Unprocessed miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Citations, etc. (Folder Ac)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Alger, Frederick Moulton, 1907-1967.
Apr. 1949, June 1949, Sept. 1949, Jan. 1950, Nov. 1950, Dec. 1950, Mar. 1951, Aug. 1951, Sept. 1951, Mar. 1952, Aug. 1952, Sept. 1952, Nov. 1952, Dec. 1952, Dec. 1954
Aten, Murl K., 1901-
Sept. 1949
Bagwell, Paul D., 1913-
Oct. 1956, July 1958, Nov. 1958
Bennett, John B. (John Bonifas), 1905-1964.
May 1950, Mar. 1951, Feb., 1952
Bentley, Alvin M. (Alvin Morrell), 1918-1969.
Aug. 1950, Jan. 1952, Sept. 1952, Dec. 1952, Aug. 1957, Oct. 1957
Blackney, William Wallace, 1876-1963.
May 1950, Mar. 1951
Bliss, Ray Charles, 1907
Oct. 1951, Feb. 1953, July 1955
Brake, D. Hale, 1891-
Sept. 1949, Oct. 1949, Oct. 1950, Dec. 1951, Sept. 1952, Feb. 1953
Brownell, Herbert, 1904-
Apr. 1954
Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.
June 1950, Apr. 1955, June 1955, July 1955, Sept. 1955, Oct. 1955
Capehart, Homer E. (Homer Earl), 1897-1979.
Mar. 1952
Carr, Leland Walker, 1883-
Apr. 1955, June 1955
Case, Francis H. (Francis Higby), 1896-1962.
Oct. 1952
Cederburg, Elford Alfred, 1918-
Feb. 1955
Chamberlain, Charles Ernest, 1917-
July 1957
Cobo, Albert Eugene, 1893-1957.
Aug. 1956, Sept. 1956, Oct. 1956, Nov. 1956.
Dirksen, Everett McKinley, 1896-1969.
Feb. 1950, Feb. 1951, Mar. 1951, June 1951, July 1951, Oct. 1951, Mar. 1952, Feb. 1953
Dondero, George Anthony, 1883-
Apr. 1949, Dec. 1949, Apr. 1950, May 1950, Aug. 1950, Nov. 1950, Mar. 1951, July 1951, Jan. 1952, Aug. 1952, Nov. 1952, Jan. 1955
Duff, James H. (James Henderson), 1883-1969.
Jan. 1951, Feb. 1951
Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), Pres. U.S., 1890-1969.
Sept. 1952, Oct. 1952, Nov. 1952, Dec. 1952. Aug. 1953, July 1956, Apr. 1957
Engel, Albert Joseph, 1888-1959.
Apr. 1949, May 1950, Sept. 1950, Oct. 1950
Farrell, Lawrence Llewellyn, 1903-1971.
Oct. 1952
Ferguson, Homer, 1889-
Apr. 1949, Aug. 1949, Dec. 1949, Jan. 1950, Dec. 1950, Jan.-Feb. 1951, Apr.-May 1951, July-Aug. 1951, Oct.-Nov. 1951, Feb.-May 1952, Aug.-Sept. 1952, Nov. -Dec. 1952, Jan.-Mar. 1953
Ford, Gerald R., 1913-
Apr. 1949, Dec. 1949, May 1950, July 1950, Aug. 1950, Sept. 1950, Nov. 1950, Mar. 1951, Dec. 1952, Dec. 1954
Ford, Henry, 1917-
Oct. 1950, Sept. 1957.
Gabrielson, Guy George, 1891-
Dec. 1950, Mar. 1951, July 1951, June 1952
Hall, Leonard Wood, 1900-
Apr. 1949, Sept. 1950, Aug. 1952, June 1953
Halleck, Charles A. (Charles Abraham), 1900-1986.
June 1951
Hannah, John A., 1902-
Nov. 1951, Feb. 1955
Hare, James M. 1910-
May 1957, July 1958
Hart, Philip A. 1912-
Dec. 1952
Hatcher, Harlan Henthorne, 1898-
Nov. 1958
Hershey, Lewis Blaine, 1893-
Nov. 1955
Hoffman, Clare Eugene, 1875-1967.
Aug. 1949, Nov. 1949, Jan.-Oct. 1950, Mar.-Apr. 1951, July 1951, Nov. 1951, Jan. 1952, Mar. 1952, Apr. 1952, July 1952, Oct. 1952, Dec. 1952, Dec. 1956
Hunt, H. L.
Mar. 1952, Apr. 1952
Jenner, William E. (William Ezra), 1908-
Jan. 1950, Dec. 1950
Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971
Jan.-Feb. 1950 Sept.-Oct. 1950, Dec. 1950, Feb. 1951, Aug. 1952
Knox, Victor Alfred, 1899-
Apr. 1949, June and July 1949, Oct. 1949, Jan. 1950, Dec. 1950, Mar. 1951, June 1951, Dec. 1952, Feb. 1955, Jan. 1957
Kohler, Walter Jodok, 1904-
Oct. 1952
Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1902-
Dec. 1951, Jan. 1952, Feb. 1952
McCarthy, Joseph, 1908-1957.
Aug. 1951, Oct. 1951, Nov. 1951
McDonald, Harry A., 1894-1964.
June 1950
McNamara, Patrick Vincent, 1894-1966.
Apr.1957
John Butlin, 1909-
Jan. 1950, June 1950, July 1950, Oct. 1950, Oct. 1951, Sept. 1952, Nov. 1952, Aug. 1954, Dec. 1955, Jan. 1956, Oct. 1956
Martin, Joseph William, 1884-1968.
June 1951, Feb. 1953
Meader, George, 1907-
Feb.-May 1951, July 1951, Feb. 1952, Apr. 1952, June 1952, Nov. 1952, Feb. 1953, Nov. 1954, Feb. 1955, Aug. 1956, Apr. 1955, June 1958
Mechem, Edward Leard, 1912-
Oct. 1951
Michener, Earl C. (Earl Corey), 1876-1957.
Aug.-Oct. 1949, Jan. 1950, May 1950, June 1950, July 1950, Sept. 1950, Mar. 1951, Apr. 1951, Aug. 1951, May 1952, Sept. 1952, Dec. 1952
Millard, Frank G. (Frank Gurnee), 1897-1976.
Jan.-Feb. 1950, Apr.-May 1950, Nov. 1950, Dec. 1950, Mar. 1951, June 1952, Sept. 1952, Nov. 1952, Feb. 1953, Apr. 1955
Milliken, William G., 1922-
Oct. 1950, Oct. 1952, Mar. 1953
Miriani, Louis C.
May 1952
Mitchell, James Paul, 1900-1964.
Nov. 1955
Mundt, Karl Earl, 1900-
Sept. 1952
Munn, Clarence Lester, 1908-
Jan. 1954
Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-
July 1951, Mar. 1952
Pollock, James Kerr, 1898-1968.
Apr. 1956
Potter, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1916-1979.
Sept. 1952, Nov. 1952, Dec. 1952, Jan.-Feb. 1955, Aug. 1955, Mar. 1956, July 1956, Nov. 1956, Jan. 1957, Apr. 1957, June 1958
Pyle, Howard, 1906-
Mar. 1952, Apr. 1952
Rogers, William Pierce, 1913-
Apr. 1957
Romney, George W., 1907-
Feb. 1952, Sept. 1957
Roth, Stephen John, 1908-
Nov. 1950
Russell, Richard B. (Richard Brevard), 1897-1971.
June 1958
Scott, Hugh Doggett, 1900-
Mar. 1949, Apr. 1949, June 1949, July 1949, July 1951
Shafer, Paul W. (Paul Werntz), 1893-1954.
Apr. 1949, May 1949, June 1949, May 1950, Sept. 1950, Mar. 1951, Apr. 1951, Aug. 1951, Feb. 1952, Dec. 1952, Apr. 1953
Sigler, Kim, 1894-1953.
June 1949, June 1950, Aug. 1950, Oct. 1951
Sink, Charles Albert, 1879-1972.
Apr. 1957
Sligh, Charles Robert, 1906-
Aug. 1952, Nov. 1952
Stassen, Harold Edward, 1907-
Aug. 1950, Sept. 1950, Feb. 1951, Dec. 1951, June 1952, Aug. 1952
Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-1972.
Aug.-Sept. 1949, Nov. 1949, Sept. 1950, Jan. 1951, Mar. 1951, Apr. 1951, Mar. Apr. 1952, July-Dec. 1952, Feb.-Mar. 1953, Oct. 1953, Nov.-Dec. 1954, Jan.-Feb. 1955, Apr.-June 1955, Aug. 1955, Oct.-Dec. 1955, Jan. 1956, Mar. 1956, May 1956, Aug.-Dec. 1956, Jan.-Mar. 1957, July-Oct. 1957, Dec. 1957, May-July 1958, Oct. 1958, Dec. 1958
Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953.
Dec. 1951, May 1952, Oct. 1952
Thompson, Ruth, 1887-1970.
Feb. 1951, June 1951, Oct. 1951, Feb. 1952
Vandenberg, William C.
Jan. 1951, Mar. 1951, Dec. 1952
Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-
Sept. 1949, Oct. 1949, Dec. 1950, Nov. 1954, May 1957
Wolcott, Jesse Paine, 1893-1969.
Nov. 1952
Woodruff, Roy Orchard, 1876-1953.
June 1949, July 1949, Aug. 1950